Preliminary Guide to the Edward C. Prescott Papers, 1964-2014 and undated RL.11204
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Edward C. Prescott papers
1964-2014 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Prescott, Edward C.
RL.11204
7.0 Linear Feet
Nobel-prize winning economist, Professor at Arizona State University, and economist at the Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis. The collection contains drafts and published copies of Prescott's research papers and other writings, professional correspondence, files from speaking engagements and presentations, and teaching materials from his career at Carnegie-Mellon University, the University of Minnesota, and Arizona State University.
Arrangement
Arranged into series: Writings, Writings by Others, Engagements, Correspondence, and Teaching Materials. Folder titles generated by creator.
Biographical / Historical
Edward C. Prescott (b. 1940) is a Nobel-prize-winning economist and professor at Arizona State University. He received the Nobel Memorial Prize in 2004 for his work in macroeconomics on the Business Cycle Theory with Finn E. Kydland.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Edward C. Prescott Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2016.
Collection Overview
The collection contains drafts and published copies of Prescott's research papers and other writings, writings by others, professional correspondence, files from speaking engagements and presentations, and teaching materials from his career at Carnegie-Mellon University, the University of Minnesota, and Arizona State University.
The Writings series contains drafts and published copies of research papers and academic articles written by Prescott and co-authors, including his 1964 dissertation "Adaptive Decision Rules for Macro Economic Planning" as well as writings with co-recipient of the Nobel Prize, Finn E. Kydland. They are arranged chronologically by publication date.
The Writings by Others series includes articles and other writings on economics collected by Prescott for his own research or interest. Arranged chronologically.
Engagements series includes materials from lectures, presentations, and speeches given by Prescott. Arranged chronologically.
Correspondence series contains letters, memos, and emails received or written by Prescott. General correspondence arranged chronologically. Other correspondence arranged by subject matter as provided by Prescott.
Teaching Materials series contains syllabi, lecture notes, exams, correspondence, and other preparatory materials for courses taught by Prescott at Carnegie-Mellon University, the University of Minnesota, and Arizona State University. Arranged chronologically.
Business cycles; Nobel Prize winners; Macroeconomics; Econometrics; Economic history; Prescott, Edward C.; Kydland, Finn E.; University of Minnesota. Dept. of Economics -- Faculty; Arizona State University -- Department of Economics; Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis
- Writings, 1964-2014; 1
  Scope and Contents
  Writings series contains drafts and published copies of research papers and academic articles written by Klein and co-authors, including his 1964 dissertation "Adaptive Decision Rules for Macro Economic Planning" as well as writings with co-recipient of the Nobel Prize, Finn E. Kydland. They are arranged chronologically by publication date.
  - Money, Multiplier-Accelerator Interaction, and the Business Cycle, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Adaptive Decision Rules for Macro Economic Planning, 1967; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Money, Multiplier Accelerator Interaction, and the Business Cycle, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Collusion in Oligopoly An Experiment on the Effect of Numbers and Information, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Collusion in the Prisoner's Dilemma: number of strategies, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Multiple Regression with Inequality Constraints Prestesting Bias Hypothesis Testing Efficiency, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Investment Under Uncertainty, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Analysis of MDTA Institutional and OJT Data Tapes for 1968, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Multiperiod Control Problem under Uncertainty, 1972 (Box 1)
  - A Note on Price Systems in Infinite Dimensional Space, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Systematic (Non-Random) Variation Models Varying Parameter Regressions: A Theory and Some Applications, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Market Structure and Monopoly Profits A Dynamic Theory, 1973 (Box 1)
  - An Adaptive Regression Model, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Tests of Adaptive Regressive Model, 1973 (Box 1)
  - The Effectiveness of MDTA Institutional Training over Time and in Periods of Unemployment MANPOWER, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Adaptive Decision Rules for Macro Economic Planning, 1974
  - Equilibrium Search and Unemployment, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Optimal Stabilization Policy: A New Formulation, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Money, Expectations and the Business Cycle, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Efficiency of the Natural Rate, 1975 (Box 1)
  - The Impact of Manpower Training on Earnings: An Econometric Analysis, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Estimation in the Presence of Stochastic Parameter Variation, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Should Control Theory Be Used for Economic Stabilization?, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Sequential Location Among Firms with Foresight, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Rules Rather than Discretion The Inconsistency of Optimal Plans, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Papers in Honor of Herbert A Simon An Introduction, 1978 (Box 1)
  - On the Possibility and Desirability of Stabilization Policy, 1978 (Box 1)
  - The Estimation of Treatment Effects for Nonrandomized Samples: The Case of Manpower Training, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Earnings and Employment Dynamics of Manpower Trainees: An Exploratory Econometrics Analysis, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Comments on the Current State of the Theory of Aggregate Investment Behavior, 1980 (Box 1)
  - A Competitive Theory of Fluctuations and the Feasibility and Desirability of Stabilization, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Equilibrium Under Uncertainty MultiAgent Statistical Decision Theory (WITH CORRECTION NOTED), 1980 (Box 1)
  - Organization Capital, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Sources of Non Diversifiable Risk*, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Recursive Competitive Equilibrium: The Case of Homogenous Households, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Time to Build and Aggregate Fluctuations, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Economic Theory, Model Size and Model Purpose, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Dynamic Optimal Taxation Rational Expectations Optimal Control, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Remarks on Methodology for Aggregate Analysis COMMENTS, 1981 (Box 1)
  - General Competitive Analysis in an Economy with Private Info, 1981 (Box 1)
  - A Test of the Intertemporal Asset Pricing Model, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Can the Cycle Be Reconciled with a Consistent Theory of Expectations, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Pareto Optima and Competitive Equilibria with Adverse Selection and Moral Hazard, 1982; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - The Equity Premium: A Puzzle, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Comments on "Economic Organization with Limited Communication" by Robert Townsend, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Dynamic Coalitions, Firm Size, and Growth, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Notes on Human Capital Growth and Unemployment, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Financial Intermediary - Coalitions, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Theory Ahead of Business Cycle Measurement, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Response to a Skeptic, 1986 (Box 2)
  - A Rejoinder to Comments on Hodrick and Prescott 1980: Post-War U.S. Business Cycles: An Empirical Investigation, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Contractual Arrangements for Intertemporal Trade, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Dynamic Coalitions: Engines of Growth, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Dynamic Coalitions Growth and the Firm, 1987; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Romer's paper "Crazy Explanations of the Productivity Slowdown," two comments, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Comment on Calibration as Estimation, 1987 (Box 2)
  - A Comment on "The New Keynesian Microfoundations", 1987 (Box 2)
  - Comment on Family Economics and Macro Behavior, 1987 (Box 2)
  - A Multiple Means of Payment Model, 1987 (Box 2)
  - An Interpretation of the Kahn-Mookerjee Efficiently Wage Model, 1987 (Box 2)
  - A Response to Bennett McCallum's Attack on Applied Real Business Cycle Theory, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Invariant Distributions for Monotone Markov Processes- WP374, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Invariant Distributions for Monotone Markov Processes- WP242, 1987 (Box 2)
  - The Work Week of Capital and its Cyclical Implications WP267, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Time Consistency and Policy, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Comments on "Economic Growth, Human Capital, and Population Growth", 1988 (Box 2)
  - Robert Solow's Neoclassical Growth Model: An Influential Contribution to Economics, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Organizations in Economic Analysis, 1988 (Box 2)
  - The Equity Premium Puzzle: A SOLUTION, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Comments on "Building Blocks of Market Clearing Business Cycle Models", 1989 (Box 2)
  - Unemployment in Computable General Equilibrium Models, 1989 (Box 2)
  - A Fortran Subroutine for Efficiently Computing HP-Filtered Time Series, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Property Rights and Dynamic Coalitions in a Theory of the Firm, 1990 (Box 2)
  - A Reconsideration of the Theory of the Firm: Dynamic Coalitions and Property Rights, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Business Cycles: Real Facts and a Monetary Myth, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Real Business Cycle Theory: What Have We Learned?, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Seigniorage as a Tax A Quantitative Evaluation, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Technology Adoption and Growth, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Hours and Employment Variations in Business Cycle Theory, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Measures of the Insurance Sector Output, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Evaluating the Welfare Effects Alternative Monetary Arrangements, 1991 (Box 2)
  - The Econometrics of the General Equilibrium Approach to Business Cycles, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Stochastic Monotonicity and Stationary Distributions for Dynamic Economies, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Banking in Computable General Equilibrium Economics, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Classical Competitive Analysis of Economies with Islands, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Insurance Contracts as Commodities.pdf, 1991 (Box 2)
  - The Econometrics of the General Equilibrium Approach to Business Cycles, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Technology Adoption and Growth, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Stochastic Monotonicity and Stationary Distributions for Dynamic Economies, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Effects of Monetary Policies An Unexpected Finding, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Changes in the Wealth of Nations, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Some Comments on the Use of General Equilibrium Theory in Aggregate Analysis, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Did Technology Shocks Cause the 1990-91 Recession?, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Cyclical Movements of the Labor Input and Its Implicit Real Wage, 1993 (Box 2)
  - The Firm and the Plant In General Equilibrium Theory, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Comments on Computable General Equilibrium Models and Monetary Policy Advice, 1994 (Box 2)
  - Barriers to Technology Adoption and Development, 1994 (Box 2)
  - Stationary Solution Overlapping Generations Model Fiat Money Experimental Evidence, 1994 (Box 2)
  - Introduction to the Symposium: The discipline of applied general equilibrium, 1995 (Box 2)
  - Equilibrium business cycles with idle resources and variable capacity utilization, 1995 (Box 2)
  - The Computational Experiment: An Econometric Tool, 1996 (Box 2)
  - Comment on Inflation Targeting in a St. Louis Model of the 21st Century, 1996 (Box 2)
  - Valuation Equilibrium with Clubs, 1997 (Box 2)
  - Real returns on government debt: a general equilibrium quantitative exploration, 1997 (Box 2)
  - On Defining Real Consumption, 1997 (Box 2)
  - Barriers to Riches, 1997 (Box 2)
  - Post-War U.S. Business Cycles: an Empirical Investigation, 1980-1997 (Box 2)
  - Business Cycle Research: Methods and Problems, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Needed: Theory of Total Factor Productivity, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Monopoly Rights A Barrier to Riches, 1997 (Box 3)
  - Comment: Some Observations on the Great Depression, 1999 (Box 3)
  - Is the Stock Market Overvalued?, 2000 (Box 3)
  - Business Cycle Research: Methods and Problems, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Taxes, Regulations, and Asset Prices, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Prosperity and Depression; 2002 Richard T. Ely Lecture (Box 3)
  - The 1990s in Japan: A Lost Decade, 2002 (Box 3)
  - Malthus to Solow, 2002 (Box 3)
  - Introduction to Sunspots and Lotteries, 2002 (Box 3)
  - Average Debt and Equity Returns Puzzling, 2003 (Box 3)
  - The Equity Premium in Retrospect, 2003 (Box 3)
  - Why do Americans Work So Much More than Europeans?, 2003 (Box 3)
  - Capacity Constraints, Asymmetries and the Business Cycle, 2004 (Box 3)
  - 1929 Stock Market Irving Fisher was Right, 2004 (Box 3)
  - Taxes, Regulations, and the Value of U.S. an U.K. Corporations, 2005 (Box 3)
  - Productivity and the Post-1990 US Economy, 2005 (Box 3)
  - Non-Convexities in Quantitative Equilibrium Studies of Business Cycles, 2005 (Box 3)
  - Unified Theory of the Evolution of International Income Levels, 2004 (Box 3)
  - Comment: Measuring Capital and Technology: An Expanded Framework, 2005 (Box 3)
  - Comments on "Inflation: Output, and Welfare" by Lagos and Rocheteau, 2005 (Box 3)
  - On the Equilibrium Concept for Overlapping Generations Organizations, 2005 (Box 3)
  - What a Country Must Do to Catch up to Industrial Leaders, 2006 (Box 3)
  - Nobel Lecture: The Transformation of Macroeconomic Policy and Research, 2006 (Box 3)
  - Some Pleasant Deficit Arithmetic, 2007 (Box 3)
  - On the Needed Quantity of Government Debt, 2006 (Box 3)
  - The Equity Premium ABCs, 2008 (Box 3)
  - Openness, Technology Capital, and Development, 2008 (Box 3)
  - Non-Risk Based Explanations Equity Premium, 2008 (Box 3)
  - U.S. Hours and Productivity Behavior Using CPS Hours Worked Data: 1947-III to 2009-III (Box 3)
  - Lifetime Aggregate Labor Supply with Endogenous Workweek length, 2009 (Box 3)
  - Intermediated Quantities and Returns, 2008 (Box 3)
  - A Note on Reforming the Financial Intermediation Sector, 2009 (Box 3)
  - Unmeasured Investment and the Puzzling US Boom in the 1990s, 2010 (Box 3)
  - Notes: Technology Capital and Spillovers, 2010 (Box 3)
  - Costly financial intermediation in neoclassical growth theory, 2011; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Aggregate Labor Supply, 2011 (Box 3)
  - More Time on the Job: the 4% Solution, 2012 (Box 4)
  - Assorted articles, op-eds, and interviews, 2004-2012 (Box 4)
  - Assorted writings and correspondence on "History of Thought", 1984-2012 (Box 4)
  - Technology Capital Transfer, 2013 (Box 4)
  - On Financing Retirement with an Aging Population, 2014 (Box 4)
- Engagements, 1983-2014 and undated; 3
  Engagements series includes materials from lectures, presentations, and speeches given by Prescott. Arranged chronologically.
  - Presentation: Quantitative Theory, undated (Box 4)
  - BYU, 1983 (Box 4)
  - Upenn, 1993 (Box 4)
  - Conference on Finance, Fluctuations, and Development, 1994 (Box 4)
  - Are Expansions Longer?, 2000 (Box 4)
  - Laurea Honoris Causa in Economia a Edward C. Prescott, Universita degli studi di Roma tor Vergata, 2002 (Box 4)
  - Commencement Univ. of Rome, 2002 (Box 4)
  - Frederic Esser Nemmers Prize in Mathematics, 2002 (Box 4)
  - AEA Ely Lecture: Prosperity and Depression, 2002 (Box 4)
  - UCSB Carl Snyder Memorial Lecture "Why do Americans Work So Much More than Europeans?", 2004 (Box 4)
  - Markets: The Only Solution to the Coming Health Crisis, 2005 (Box 4)
  - Presentation of Comments on "Indivisible Labor, Lotteries, and Personal Savings", 2006 (Box 4)
  - Glen Falls High School Graduation Address, 2006 (Box 4)
  - Address for Edward Mallinckodt University Professorship in Arts and Sciences, Wash U, 2007 (Box 4)
  - Festschrift for Robert E. Lucas, 2007 (Box 4)
  - Neoclassical Growth Theory: From Swan to Now, 2014 (Box 4)
  - Importance of Good Governance for Economic Prosperity, 2014 (Box 4)
- Writings by Others, 1983-2012 and undated; 2
  Writings by Others series includes articles featuring Prescott as well as other articles and writings on economics collected by Prescott for his own research or interest. Arranged chronologically.
  - The Evolution of the Kyland-Prescott research program: transformation, recollections, and documents by Warren Young, undated (Box 4)
  - Articles and interviews featuring Prescott, 1983-2012 (Box 4)
  - Assorted op-eds and articles saved by Prescott, 1999-2012 (Box 4)
- Correspondence, 1982-2013; 4
  Correspondence series contains letters, memos, and emails received or written by Prescott. General correspondence arranged chronologically. Other correspondence arranged by subject matter as provided by Prescott.
  - General correspondence, 1982-1998 (Box 4)
  - General correspondence, 1999-2013 (Box 4)
  - Research correspondence, 1990-2007 (Box 4)
  - University of Minnesota, 1995-2005 (Box 4)
  - UCLA, Upenn, 1998 (Box 4)
  - MIT - Barriers to Riches, 1999 (Box 4)
  - Referees reports, 1992-1995 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence from Robert E. Lucas, 1981-1982 (Box 4)
  - Requests for reprints of writings, 1991-2001 (Box 4)
- Teaching Materials, 1982-2012; 5
  Teaching Materials series contains syllabi, lecture notes, exams, correspondence, and other preparatory materials for courses taught by Prescott at Carnegie-Mellon University, the University of Minnesota, and Arizona State University. Arranged chronologically.
  - Carnegie-Mellon EC 8105, 8106, 0-87, 1982 (Box 4)
  - UMN Econ 5141 Final Exam, Spring 1982 (Box 4)
  - UMN Econ 5721, 5741, Business Cycles, 1982-1994 (Box 4)
  - UMN Econ 5141 Final Exam, Spring 1983 (Box 4)
  - Business Cycles (574H, 4749), 1986, 1998-1999 (Box 4)
  - UMN Econ 5152 Economics of Economic Analysis, 1989-1994 (Box 4)
  - UMN students, UMN Department of Economics, 1995-1999 (Box 4)
  - Monetary Prelims, Spring 1995 (Box 4)
  - UMN Econ 239 Quantitative Analysis of the Macroeconomy, 1998 (Box 4)
  - Kyland Mini-Semester, 1998 (Box 4)
  - Macroeconomics, Preliminary Examination, 1998, 2002, 2006 (Box 4)
  - UMN Econ405 Theory of Income III, Exercises, Syllabus, Spring 1999 (Box 4)
  - Macro Theory III, 2000 (Box 4)
  - UMN Econ 8107, Macroeconomic heory III, Spring 2002 (Box 4)
  - Arizona State University, Econ 494, Advanced Macroeconomics, Spring 2005-2006 (Box 4)
  - Arizona State University, Graduate Course: Topics in Growth and Development, Spring 2005, Outlie and Reading Exams, and Student Exercises (Box 4)
  - Arizona State University, ECN 494 Advanced Macroeconomics, Spring 2005, Syllabus, Exercises, Exams, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Arizona State University, ECN 494 Advanced Macroeconomics, Spring 2006, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Arizona State University, ECN 413 Advanced Macroeconomics, 2007-2012 (Box 5)
  - Arizona State University, ECN 791, Spring 2012 (Box 5)
  - Arizona State University, Ph.D. Qualifying Exams, 2012 (Box 5)